Hammond World Atlas Corporation archive of print records and samples of printing methods.
Geography & Map Division Library of Congress
Hammond World Atlas Corporation archive of print records and samples of printing methods. 1900-1999
G70.2 coll Hammond
Hammond Incorporated
65 boxes (52 linear ft.)
Geography & Map Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The Hammond World Atlas Corporation archival collection consists of map sculptures, printing separations, and business records (index cards) that document the 100-year publishing history of the company. Hammond was known for its extensive line of world, historical, school, and thematic atlases, but the company also issued a wide variety of other cartographic items, including maps, globes, and transparencies during the last 100 years. It printed numerous other works, primarily for the educational market. In addition to its own imprints, Hammond's cartographic output was included in the encyclopedias, almanacs, dictionaries, religous texts, and textbooks of many other publishers.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
Organizations
Hammond Incorporated.
Subjects
Cartography--History.; Printing--History.
Form/Genre
Manuscript maps.; Maps.
Provenance
In December 2002, the collection was donated by the American Map Corporation, part of the Langenscheidt Publishing Group.
Access and Restrictions
The [ammond World Atlas Corporation archive of print records and samples of printing methods is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Geography & Map Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Background Note
Founded by Caleb Stillson Hammond in 1900, and formally incorporated in 1901, the company has been known over much of its history as C.S. Hammond & Co. Unlike most map publishing in the United States, which was centered in Chicago at the beginning of the twentieth century, C.S. Hammond began work in New York City, and the company has continued to maintain its headquarters in that area.
In the mid-1980s, Hammond led the industry in the development of a computer-assisted mapmaking system by creating a database that contained the latitude and longitude of all the geographic features on their maps. The proprietary database was further enhanced by patented methods for line-smoothing and name placement and culminated with the publication in 1992 of the first all-digital world atlas, "Hammond's Atlas of the World."
The company was privately owned by the Hammond family until its assets were acquired by Langenscheidt Publishers Inc. in 1999.
Scope and Content Note
Consists of relief models (terrasculptures), samples of book cover prints, negatives, page mock ups, sets of index cards that contain information on print runs, samples of catalogs, and an obituary of C.S. Hammond.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized in three series
Series I Terrasculpture Models
Series II Examples of the Print Process
Series III Printing Records: Index Cards
Container List
- Terrasculpture Models (Box 1-50)
  Consists of 51 physical relief models called "terrasculptures." Created in the late 1960s by Ernst Hofmann, a long-time head of cartographic design at Hammond, the terrasculptures are thin aluminum sheets which have been manually embossed to simulate the earth's surface in three-dimensional form. By raising the surface of the aluminum sheets to depict elevated features, or depressing the sheets to reflect such features as rivers and sea floor depths, these models accurately represent relief and topography. Color can be applied to the models to reflect the earth's natural vegetation. Hofmann's relief models reveal the artistic skills that are traditionally a major component of mapmaking. Once the relief sculptures were completed, they were photographed to provide the base shaded relief found on the Hammond maps, creating the impression that the relief actually rises from the printed page. Using the same aluminum modeling technique, Hofmann also created an 18-inch diameter globe, called the "terrasphere."
  - Mauritius and Reunion (Box 1)
  - Honolulu (Box 2)
  - Cape Verde (Box 3)
  - Hawaiian Islands (Box 4)
  - Israel (Box 5)
  - Samoa and Tahiti (Box 6)
  - Santiago (Box 7)
  - Rio de la Plata (Box 8)
  - Mexico City and Veracruz (Box 9)
  - West Irian (West New Guinea) (Box 10)
  - Beijing (Box 11)
  - Manilla (Box 12)
  - Mexico City (Box 13)
  - Tampa-Orlando (Box 14)
  - Shanghai (Box 15)
  - Witwatersrand, South Africa (Box 16)
  - Capetown (Box 17)
  - D.B.W. Layout J (Box 18)
  - Atlanta (Box 19)
  - Montreal (Box 20)
  - Minneapolis (Box 21)
  - Southeastern Brazil (Box 22)
  - New Zealand (Box 23)
  - Houston (Box 24)
  - Alaska Hawaii inset (Box 25)
  - Iceland (Box 26)
  - Galapagos (Box 27)
  - Cleveland Pittsburgh (Box 28)
  - Untitled (Box 29)
  - Toronto Buffalo (Box 30)
  - Caracas (Box 31)
  - Dallas Ft. Worth (Box 32)
  - D.B.W. Layout G (Galilee) (Box 33)
  - Madagascar (Box 34)
  - Caribbean (Box 35)
  - Southern Brazil (Box 36)
  - Southern India (Box 37)
  - Upper Danube (Box 38)
  - Seattle/San Francisco (Box 39)
  - Tokyo Osaka (Box 40)
  - Central Asia (Box 41)
  - "South" (Box 42)
  - Northeast Africa (Box 43)
  - Spain and Portugal (Box 44)
  - New Zealand (Box 45)
  - Central Alps (Box 46)
  - Northwestern France (Box 47)
  - Southeast Asia Northern Part (Box 48)
  - South Asia (Box 49)
  - OVERSIZE United States (Box 50)
- Examples of the Print Process (Box 51)
  Within eight folders are samples of materials illustrate and document all the basic elements of map compilation, design, construction and printing. Map artwork contained in the collection includes works drafted using pen and ink, stick-up lettering, and a scribing technique that creates the desired image by removing an opaque coating from a sheet of plastic film. Cartographic design features include examples of line work, symbolization and lettering. The printing of maps and atlases is represented in numerous printing plates, color separations, photographs of original artwork and film negatives. Also included are plates of book covers and catalogs, as well as, an obituary of C.S. Hammond.
  - The New Peerless Atlas of the World Atlas cover on board (Folder 1)
  - The New Era Atlas of the World Atlas cover on board (Folder 1)
  - Hammond's Pictorial Atlas of the World Atlas cover on board (Folder 1)
  - The People's Atlas with 1920 Census Atlas cover on board (Folder 1)
  - Hammond's Commercial and Library Atlas of the World wuth 1910 Census Atlas cover on board (Folder 1)
  - Faultlines and Earthquake Map, California Atlas proofs, negatives (Folder 2)
  - Northern Japan Ryuku Island proofs, negatives (Folder 2)
  - Western Europe proofs, negatives (Folder 2)
  - Antarctica Cross Section Original Art (Folder 3)
  - Germany Original Art Before WWI, Between Wars, Occupied (Folder 3)
  - Switzerland Original Art Language map (Folder 3)
  - Terrasculpture Globe Gore proofs, negatives (Folder 4)
  - South America proofs, negatives Vegetation relief as used in new format atlases (Folder 4)
  - Russia proofs, negatives, sketches (Folder 4)
  - General Catalogue 1890s? (Folder 5)
  - Catalogue to Road Maps (Folder 6)
  - Catalogue of Atlases, Maps, Globes, and Geographical Appliances. 1929 (Folder 7)
  - C.S. Hammond obituary 1929 (Folder 8)
- Printing Records: Index Cards 1900-1990s
  Among the non-cartographic materials in the collection is a file of some 12,000 4-by-6-inch cards that represent part of Hammond's printing history from the early 1900s to the mid-1990s. This is primarily a record of the publications that Hammond produced for other companies. The basic data contained in these records changed over time but usually included such information as the customer's name, type of material printed, and number of copies printed, which could range from a few hundred to hundreds of thousands of copies.
  - Index cards: 1900s-1950s (Box 52-57)
  - Index cards: 1950s-1960s (Box 58-60)
  - Index cards: 1960s-1970s (Box 61-62)
  - Index cards: 1960s-1990s (Box 63)
  - Index cards: "inactive" (Box 64-65)